Finding Aid for Michigan Land Use Institute records, 1995-2007
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Policy Files
  - Office of the Policy Specialist-Mac McClelland
    - Neighborhood Schools Project
      - Charlevoix Public Schools-Legal, 2000; 2 folders (Box 30)
      - Charlevoix /Harbor Springs, 2000 (Box 30)
      - Clippings, 1998-2004; 4 folders (Box 30)
      - Dexter Community Schools, 1998 (Box 30)
      - Empire School Proposal (Box 30)
      - Grand Rapids Education Enterprise Zones, 2003 (Box 30)
      - Hard Lessons Report, 2003 (Box 30)
      - Holt High School, 2000 (Box 30)
      - Jackson High School, 1999 (Box 30)
      - Livonia Schools, 2003; 4 folders (Box 30)
      - Meeting Notes, 2004 (Box 30)
      - Michigan Historic Preservation Network Conference-Kalamazoo, 2003 (Box 30)
      - Michigan Public Educational Facilities, 2002 (Box 30)
      - National Resources, 2002 (Box 31)
      - Northville Schools, 2001; 2 folders (Box 31)
      - Okemos High School, 2003 (Box 31)
      - Otwell, Bob, 1999 (Box 31)
      - People and Land (PAL) Grant Development, 2001 (Box 31)
      - PAL Schools Grant, 2004 (Box 31)
      - PAL Workshop, 2003 (Box 31)
      - Presentations and Reports, 2003 (Box 31)
      - Related Articles and Reports, 2003-2004; 2 folders (Box 31)
      - Report (Neighborhood Schools Report), 2003; 2 folders (Box 31)
      - Safe Routes to School, 2004 (Box 31)
      - State Land Use Group, 2000 (Box 31)
      - Williamston Schools, 2003 (Box 31)
    - Policy
      - House Bill 5660 (Box 31)
      - Neighborhood Enterprise Zones, 2002-2003 (Box 31)
      - MSU Land Use Project (Box 31)
      - Smart Code (Box 31)
      - United Cerebral Palsy Data (Box 31)
      - United Cerebral Policy Land Use Policy Project, 2004-2005 (Box 31)
    - South Haven Schools -- Joyce Petter Files (Box 32)
      - South Haven Schools, 2003 (Box 32)
      - Class Size Background Research, 2003; 2 folders (Box 32)
      - Dropouts, 2002 (Box 32)
      - Email Correspondence, 2002-2003 (Box 32)
      - Enrollment Projections, 2002 (Box 32)
      - Facilities, 2001-2002 (Box 32)
      - Facility Board Advisory Group, 2002-2003 (Box 32)
      - Facilities Committee, 2002 (Box 32)
      - Floor Plans (Box 32)
      - Greiner Report, 2001 (Box 32)
      - Program Requirements, 2001 (Box 32)
      - Scenarios, 2002 (Box 32)
      - Scenarios Poll, 2002 (Box 32)
      - Standard & Poor's Evaluation Report, 2002 (Box 32)
  - Office of the Transportation Policy Coordinator-Kelly Thayer
    - Miscellaneous
      - Lands Legacy Initiative, 1999 (Box 33)
      - Land Use and Sprawl, 1999 (Box 33)
      - Lawsuits, 1998 (Box 33)
      - Leelanau County, 1999 (Box 33)
      - Local Government Commission (Box 33)
      - Michigan Environmental Council, 2001 (Box 33)
      - Maintenance-Michigan Roads and Bridges, 1999-2001 (Box 33)
      - Miscellaneous, 2000 (Box 33)
      - News Clippings, 1998-2000; 2 folders (Box 33)
      - Public Transit Detroit, 1999-2001 (Box 33)
      - Public Transit-Grand Rapids, 2000 (Box 33)
      - Public Transit-Michigan, 2000 (Box 33)
      - Rail Service in Michigan, 1999-2000 (Box 33)
      - Route 50 Corridor, 1996-1997 (Box 33)
      - Safety-Roads, 2000 (Box 33)
      - Sprawl and Transportation, 1999-2002 (Box 33)
      - State Roads-News Articles, 1999 (Box 33)
      - Statistics, 1997 (Box 33)
      - Surface Transportation Policy Project, 1997-2000; 4 folders (Box 33)
      - Taxes, 2000 (Box 33)
      - Transportation Equity Act, 2001 (Box 33)
    - Traverse City Bypass
      - 3 Mile Road Project, 1998-1999 (Box 34)
      - 3 Mile Road Project Grant Applications, 1998 (Box 34)
      - Army Corps of Engineers, 2000-2001 (Box 34)
      - Articles, 1998-2001; 3 folders (Box 34)
      - Cass Bridge Replacement, 1997 (Box 34)
      - Cass Bridge Replacement Environmental Assessment, 1997 (Box 34)
      - Citizens Advisory Committee (CAC), 1999-2000; 2 folders (Box 34)
      - CAC Mobility Study, 1996 (Box 34)
      - Draft Environmental Impact Statement (DEIS), 1999-2001 (Box 34)
      - DEIS Concurrence, 1999-2000 (Box 34)
      - Department of Environmental Quality, 1995-2000 (Box 34)
      - Documents (Box 34)
      - Environmental Assessment, 1997 (Box 34)
      - Environmental Protection Agency, 2000-2001 (Box 34)
      - Federal Government, 1997-2001 (Box 34)
      - Fish And Wildlife Service, 2001 (Box 34)
      - JJR, Inc., 1998-2000 (Box 34)
      - Kuner, Rick, 1999 (Box 34)
      - Legal, 1997-2001 (Box 35)
      - Local Government, 1999 (Box 35)
      - Maps (Box 35)
      - Michigan Department of Transportation (MDOT), 2001-2003 (Box 35)
      - Transportation Modeling, 1997 (Box 35)
      - Press Releases, 1999-2001 (Box 35)
      - Public Letters, 2001 (Box 35)
      - Road Commission, 1996-2001; 2 folders (Box 35)
      - Smart Roads, 1996-1999 (Box 35)
      - Smart Roads Correspondence, 1998-1999 (Box 35)
      - State Historic Preservation Office, 1999 (Box 35)
      - Supplemental Comments, 1996-2001 (Box 35)
      - Traverse City Area Transportation and Land Use Study, 2000 (Box 35)
      - Traverse City Bypass-Technical (Box 35)
      - Traverse City Roads-Articles, 2000-2001 (Box 35)
      - Tribal Concerns, 2001 (Box 35)
- Program Files
  The Program Files, 1996-2005, contain the records of the Leelanau Smart Growth Program Organizer, Johanna Miller; Entrepreneurial Agriculture Program Director, Patty Cantrell; Program Development Director, Keith Schneider; and Program Director, Jim Lively. The Johanna Miller files focus on growing community support for and implementing Smart Growth principles in Leelanau County. The Patty Cantrell files contain documentation of MLUI's Entrepreneurial Agriculture program, a program designed to promote small-scale, entrepreneurial agricultural practices in Michigan. The Keith Schneider files contain program files focusing on growth management and land use and MLUI's role in the 2004 debate over beach access and the public use of the Lake Michigan lakeshore. Jim Lively's files are subdivided into the sub-subseries Smart Growth, covering the implementation of Smart Growth principles in the United States, Wetlands Protection, and two series documenting the Institute's role in protecting Michigan's natural resources for public use--the South Fox Island and Whitefish Point sub-subseries.
  - Leelanau Smart Growth Program Organizer-Johanna Miller
    - Leelanau Smart Growth Program
      - Leelanau Smart Growth Coalition, 2003 (Box 36)
      - 501 c.3 Rules, 2004 (Box 36)
      - Ad Council, 2005 (Box 36)
      - Community Design (Box 36)
      - Communications Protocols (Box 36)
      - Conservation Summit, 2002 (Box 36)
      - Elmwood, 2004 (Box 36)
      - Emmet Country News, 2005 (Box 36)
      - Emmet Office Set Up, 2005 (Box 36)
      - Emmet: Petoskey Area Open Space, 2005 (Box 36)
      - Empire, 1999-2000 (Box 36)
      - Enterprise Articles, 2003-2004 (Box 36)
      - Events, 2004 (Box 36)
      - Past Events, 2003 (Box 36)
      - Farmland Protection, 2003 (Box 36)
      - Foundations/Grants, 2003-2004 (Box 36)
      - Fundraising, 2003 (Box 36)
      - Fundraising Ideas-Hartman-Hammond, 2005 (Box 36)
      - Fundraiser Pro, 2004 (Box 36)
      - General Plan Update (Box 36)
      - Glen Arbor, 2004 (Box 36)
      - Glen Lake, 2004 (Box 36)
      - Historic Preservation Information, 2005 (Box 36)
      - Homestead Land Swap, 2002 (Box 36)
      - Interns, 2004 (Box 36)
      - Lake Leelanau Marina, 2001 (Box 36)
      - Lawmakers' Letters, 2002 (Box 36)
      - Leadership Council, 2004 (Box 36)
      - Media List, 2004 (Box 36)
      - Member Communication, 2004 (Box 36)
      - New Designs (Box 36)
      - Northport, 2002-2003 (Box 36)
      - Play to Win-Leelanau Smart Growth Coalition Presentation, 2002 (Box 36)
      - Smart Growth Principles (Box 36)
      - Templates, 2002 (Box 36)
      - Today's Tomorrows, 2002-2003 (Box 36)
      - Wealth Engine (Box 36)
  - Office of the Entrepreneurial Agriculture Program Director-Patty Cantrell
    - Entrepreneurial Agriculture (Box 37)
      - Agriculture, 1994-2000 (Box 37)
      - Clippings, 2002-2005; 3 folders (Box 37)
      - Electronic Files (Box 37)
      - Right to Farm Michigan, 2003 (Box 37)
    - Program Files
      - Air, Coal, Mercury, 2003-2004; 2 folders (Box 37)
      - Beach Access, 2004-2005; 6 folders (Box 37)
      - Coal Plant, 2003-2004 (Box 37)
      - Detroit NAACP, 2003 (Box 37)
      - Global Climate Change, 2004; 2 folders (Box 37)
      - Granholm, Jennifer, 2003-2004; 3 folders (Box 38)
      - Growth Management, 2000-2001
        - California (Box 38)
        - Colorado (Box 38)
        - Florida (Box 38)
        - Georgia (Box 38)
        - Idaho (Box 38)
        - Illinois (Box 38)
        - Maine (Box 38)
        - Maryland (Box 38)
        - Maryland-Census Data (Box 38)
        - Maryland-Glendening (Box 38)
        - Massachusetts (Box 38)
        - Michigan (Box 38)
        - Michigan-News Articles (Box 38)
        - Minnesota (Box 38)
        - Montana (Box 38)
        - New Jersey (Box 38)
        - New Mexico (Box 38)
        - New York (Box 38)
        - Oregon (Box 38)
        - Ohio (Box 39)
        - Pennsylvania (Box 39)
        - Rhode Island (Box 39)
        - Sources and Data (Box 39)
        - South Carolina (Box 39)
        - United States Environmental Protection Agency (Box 39)
        - Utah (Box 39)
        - Vermont (Box 39)
        - Virginia (Box 39)
        - Washington State (Box 39)
        - Wisconsin (Box 39)
        - Smart Growth America (Box 39)
      - Gubernatorial Campaign, 2002 (Box 39)
      - History (Box 39)
      - Milan Railway, 1999 (Box 39)
      - Natural Resources Defense Council, Wastewater, 2004 (Box 39)
      - Nelson, Gaylord, 2004 (Box 39)
      - New York Times, Small Agriculture, 2004 (Box 39)
      - News Desk Interns, 2004 (Box 39)
      - Sulfide Mining, 2004 (Box 39)
      - Wal-mart, 2004 (Box 39)
      - Wolves, 2005 (Box 39)
  - Office of the Program Director-Jim Lively
    - Smart Growth
      - Benzie County, 1997-2004; 2 folders (Box 40)
      - Benzie Sewer Study, 2000 (Box 40)
      - Citizens for Positive Planning, 2002-2003; 2 folders (Box 40)
      - Coastal Management Program, 2003 (Box 40)
      - Coordinated Planning, 2000-2002; 2 folders (Box 40)
      - Emmet County, 2002-2003 (Box 40)
      - Leelanau Courthouse, 2004 (Box 40)
      - Manistee County, 1996-2002 (Box 40)
      - Michigan Land Research Project, 2001 (Box 40)
      - Rotary Proposal, 2002 (Box 40)
    - South Fox Island
      - South Fox Is, 2000-2003; 6 folders (Box 41)
      - Articles, 1998-2002; 3 folders (Box 41)
      - Convergence Documents (Box 41)
      - Department of Environmental Quality Road Proposal, 2000 (Box 41)
      - Department of Natural Resources, 2000-2001 (Box 41)
      - Government Documents (FOIA Requests), 3 folders (Box 41)
      - History of Fox Islands (Box 41)
      - Land Swap-South Tip (Box 41)
      - Land Swap-Transparency (Box 41)
      - Litigation, 2003; 2 folders (Box 41)
      - Notes, 2000 (Box 41)
      - Photos, 2000 (Box 41)
    - Wetlands Protection
      - Crystal Lake Boat Launch, 2003-2004; 3 folders (Box 42)
      - Traverse City Bridge, 2003-2004; 3 folders (Box 42)
      - Traverse City Bridge Report, 2003; 2 folders (Box 42)
      - Traverse City Bridge-TALUS Tech Committee, 2004 (Box 42)
    - Whitefish Point
      - Whitefish Point, 2000-2002; 7 folders (Box 43)
      - Administrative Records, 3 folders (Box 43)
      - Archeological Survey, 1983 (Box 43)
      - Audubon Society Materials (Box 43)
      - Coast Guard Letters and Memos, 1973-1990 (Box 43)
      - Comprehensive Plan, 1992; 2 folders (Box 43)
      - Correspondence, 2002; 3 folders (Box 44)
      - Correspondence-Historical Status, 1973-2001 (Box 44)
      - Correspondence-U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service, 1997-2000 (Box 44)
      - Environmental Assessment, 1983-2001 (Box 44)
      - Gravel Parking Lot Plan (Box 44)
      - Land Transfer (Box 44)
      - Legal Parameters, 2002 (Box 44)
      - List File, 2000 (Box 44)
      - Litigation File, 2002; 2 folders (Box 44)
      - Management Plan, 2002 (Box 44)
      - Minutes from Meetings and Community Forums, 1997-2000 (Box 44)
      - Natural Inventory, 2002 (Box 44)
      - Permits and Agreements, 2000 (Box 44)
      - Photographs (Box 44)
      - Press Clippings, 2001 (Box 44)
      - Public Use Management Plan Drafts, 2002 (Box 44)
      - Resource Protection Handbook (Box 44)
      - Septic, 2002 (Box 44)
      - Signatures, 2002 (Box 44)
- Visual and Electronic Materials
  The Visual and Electronic Materials, series contains photographs of MLUI staff and events as well as slides and negatives of similar material. It also includes two VHS tapes, original material used in the Institute's magazine The Great Lakes Bulletin, and electronic files.
  - Photographs
    - 1996-2000, 10 folders (Box 45)
    - Undated, 5 folders (Box 45)
    - Undated, 13 folders (Box 46)
    - Negatives (Box 46)
  - Various Materials
    - Publication Materials (Box 47)
      - Arcadia Golf Course (Box 47)
      - Great Lakes Bulletin Art, 2 folders (Box 47)
      - Great Lakes Bulletin Layouts (Box 47)
      - MLUI Publications (Box 47)
      - MTLC Logo Art (Box 47)
    - Slides, Undated; 1 folders; 1 boxes (Box 47)
    - VHS videotapes
      - Governor's Office of Smart Growth Video (Box 47)
      - Michigan at Risk Documentary (Box 47)
    - Electronic Materials
      - Electronic Files, 1 boxes (Box 47)